[{"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is the difference between data profiling and data mining?", "answers": ["Fintech data analysts work with and manipulate data in many different ways. The interviewer wants to make sure that you know the difference between data profiling - which involves assessing any flaws in your data - and data mining - which refers to looking for patterns and trends within cleansed data. If possible, give examples of times when you've profiled or mined data.", "\"To me, I associate data profiling with cleansing the data. It is the step that I take before I clean my data. In other words, first I search for any consistency or logic errors in my data (that is, profile the data), and then I remove those flaws (that is, cleanse my data). Data mining, on the other hand, is something that comes toward the end of the process, whereby I look at the data in search of anomalies, patterns, and correlations that allow me to draw useful conclusions I can then share with my manager.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Tell me about a time when you had to deal with a tight deadline. What did you do?", "answers": ["Like any industry, there will be times as a fintech data analyst when you need to deal with tight or shifting deadlines. The interviewer wants to know that you can manage this when the situation arises. If possible, give an example of a time when you successfully handled a challenging or changed deadline. Explain how you deal with the stress while ensuring a positive outcome.", "\"In my previous role, there were frequently times when my team and I encountered challenging deadlines. In fact, during earnings season we had to parse numerous SEC filings as they came in and do so quickly so our clients received up-to-date information in a timely manner. During the heat of earnings, there would be a ton of filings coming in. To stay ahead of the game, we would schedule shifts throughout the day and night for each person on the team. These shifts allowed for everyone to take necessary breaks as needed but kept coverage going of the filings. We did this repeatedly and it became second nature. I don't stress out with tight deadlines; instead, I look for solutions and then execute as needed to ensure the work gets done properly.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is the worst job you've ever had and why?", "answers": ["The interviewer is looking for a specific personality type to fill this role: someone who is analytical and detail-oriented, in addition to being someone who doesn't get bored when working with large datasets for several hours at a time. This question helps the interviewer determine if you fit into this mold or not. You will want to avoid talking negatively about a job that you found tedious, particularly one that involves data or numbers, as this will indicate to the interviewer that you will likely get bored within the fintech data analyst position.", "\"The worst job I ever had was when I was a teenager, and I worked as a cashier at an amusement park concession stand. I disliked the job because it was very noisy and busy. It also involved a lot of social interaction, and while I enjoy working with others at times, I prefer to work independently in a quiet atmosphere with fewer distractions. Working with data is something that I really enjoy; I like the mental challenge of it, as well as reaching different milestones throughout the project, like after I successfully validate the data or discover a new trend during the data mining stage.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is data verification and why is it necessary?", "answers": ["Fintech data analysts must validate the accuracy, consistency, and clarity of their data at the onset of a project in order to mitigate incorrectly drawn conclusions later on. The interviewer is testing your knowledge around data verification, including how it's performed and why one needs to do it in the first place. Talk them through how you typically validate your data and why you do it.", "\"I always validate my data because I know that imperfect, unvalidated data will likely lead to flawed business decisions down the line. And not only do I make sure to verify the data inputs and values themselves, but I also validate the data model so I don't run into issues later on using my data files in various applications and programs. I typically use validation rules that check for consistency around data type, range, uniqueness, consistent expressions, and null values, in addition to formatting rules that validate the structure of my data. \""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What's an area you'd like to improve in?", "answers": ["This question is essentially a way for an interviewer to inquire about your weaknesses without asking directly. Think of an area or skill in your work life that you know could be improved. Talk about how you plan to learn and gain more experience in this area so you can become a better fintech data analyst.", "\"By nature, I like to work independently so I'd say that one area where I could improve is working as part of a team. I'm happiest when my manager gives me a project and the freedom to complete it as I see fit. This autonomy gives me full control over the outcome of the project, and I like that because I have a strong work ethic and perfectionist tendencies. I definitely get along with my colleagues on a personal level and can work on a team with them as needed. But this is an area that could use improvement since I don't do it all the time and generally prefer to work alone. I know that working with others provides different perspectives that can ultimately make the project process and outcome better.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Let's say that you're asked to work directly with a client about implementing a new data feed. How would you handle this?", "answers": ["Most fintech data analysts don't spend much time interfacing directly with clients; that job tends to be left up to customer support, sales, and account management. However, there may be times when it's necessary for you to communicate with a client to resolve a technical issue or to implement a new data-related feature for them. Talk the interviewer through the steps you would take to help the client.", "\"While I generally prefer to be behind my desk, plugging away at my latest data project, I am open to working directly with clients as well. In this type of scenario, I would begin by discussing expectations with my manager and then arranging a call or Zoom meeting with the client in question. During this initial call or meeting, I would find out exactly what the client needs, answer any questions, and provide them with a timeline for when they can expect the feature to be implemented. If it is a straightforward request, I'd hang up and incorporate the project into my workload and look to finish it as soon as possible. If the request requires collaboration with others, I would schedule times to speak with those other analysts. In the end, I would work efficiently and quickly to implement the data feed that the client expects and my manager approves. I always aim to completely satisfy the customer and my manager.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Do you prefer to work independently or as part of a team?", "answers": ["It's best to answer this question honestly because a match between your preference and the company's needs will make you happier down the road. Many times data analysts work in teams to complete projects, but there are also many instances when data analysts work primarily by themselves - it depends on the company and its culture. There is no right or wrong answer here; be truthful so both you and the interviewer can determine if this will be a good fit or not.", "\"Honestly, I prefer to work alone, although I am definitely a team player and willing to contribute to a team when needed. When I'm working independently, I like that I'm in full control and can make all the decisions without having to stop and consult someone else. I also enjoy being able to hand in a completed project that is exactly the way I want it. However, having said that, I definitely recognize that it can be very helpful to hear someone else's perspective, so whenever I'm unsure I don't hesitate to ask a team member or manager for their thoughts.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What kind of problems do fintech data analysts encounter during projects?", "answers": ["There are some common issues that fintech data analysts run into time and time again. The interviewer wants to find out if you've experienced these problems yourself during projects and, if you did, how you fixed them. If possible, provide examples and explain what you do to avoid these kinds of issues.", "\"I think part of conducting data analysis is accepting that issues are going to crop up. One needs to try to avoid these problems in the first place, but if they do arise, it's a matter of knowing how to handle them so ultimately your end result is accurate. One issue that frequently comes up is duplicate data entries and spelling mistakes. This is only natural given that people make mistakes when they enter information into databases. I run validation rules to catch and eliminate these kinds of errors. Sometimes the data source isn't reliable, in which case much more time needs to spent cleansing the data. To avoid this, I try to use only reliable and quality sources to obtain my data. Incomplete data creates problems, and another common issue occurs when data is gathered from multiple sources. In this case, it's a matter of structuring the various datasets so they are all compatible and don't cause any delays when I perform the analysis.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Why are you leaving your current job?", "answers": ["This question can provide the interviewer with insight into why you're looking to make a career move. You'll want to explain your reasoning and motivation behind moving into a fintech data analyst role if you're coming from a different kind of career. If you're coming from a similar type of role, discuss what appeals to you about this specific company. Whatever you do, don't talk negatively about your past job, employer, or coworkers as this can leave a bad impression.", "\"As you can see from my resume, I've been a data analyst for several years now, just not in the fintech field. And I've enjoyed my time as a data analyst; I truly believe that this is what I'm meant to do. I love delving into new datasets and extracting valuable business insights. But I'm particularly interested in switching to your company because of my passion for investing and finance. While I enjoy crunching any numbers, I am most interested in analyzing data that is related to investing because it's a topic of immense interest to me. I have also researched what your company does and would like to help it succeed by analyzing whatever datasets will help it excel, whether they be sales- or marketing-related. Essentially, I'm looking to make a move because I'm really interested in what your company does.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is the most important skill you've learned in your career?", "answers": ["There are many different answers you can give to this question. Whichever skill you choose to focus on, be sure to explain why you picked it and why you feel it has been so important to your career. Some possible skills you could choose to talk about include diligence, communication, patience, organization, perseverance, integrity, knowledge about SQL, time or resource management, or interpersonal skills, among many others.", "\"I think the most important skill I have learned during my career is perseverance. The reason being that as a fintech data analyst, I have to stick with what I'm working on despite any obstacles or frustrations that arise in order to derive meaningful business insights at the end. If I give up in the middle of a project because I'm tired of looking at all the data or because the quality of the data isn't as good as I had anticipated, then I never get anywhere. No matter what, I have to keep working on the problem or question until I come to a resolution. If I don't do this, there's no way I can be a great data analyst. But it has taken practice and a commitment to teaching myself to keep going in all cases.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Why should we hire you over other candidates?", "answers": ["Prior to the interview, you should rehearse your answer to a question like this one. You need to be able to sell yourself and clearly explain why you deserve the job over someone else. Practice your answer so you can speak confidently and smoothly. Make sure to emphasize your relevant experience, academic degrees, and personality traits and explain why you will excel in the role.", "\"You should hire me over others because I have in-depth experience in data analysis, a passion for fintech, and a degree in mathematics, all of which will help me to succeed. By nature, I'm also highly analytical, detail-oriented, and patient. I don't get bored easily; instead, I truly enjoy working with large datasets for hours at a time. I know how to proactively handle stress and will take appropriate breaks to recharge. I am also intelligent and will find meaningful insights in the data that will help your company succeed. Finally, I am motivated, take initiative, and have a strong work ethic. You can count on me to work hard day in and day out to get the job done right for you.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is data cleansing and why is it important?", "answers": ["It is imperative that a fintech data analyst understand how important it is that the data they work with be free of inconsistencies and errors, especially in the fintech field where bad data can result in lost clients and big costs to the company. The interviewer wants to know that you understand how to cleanse data and why it's necessary to do so.", "\"Throughout my college career and the internships I've completed, if there's one thing that I've learned it's that only good data will give you good results. Naturally, high-quality data is data that has had all errors and inconsistencies removed from it. One way I clean data is to segregate it by certain characteristics so I can then look at similar data grouped together. This is also helpful because it puts the data into smaller groups, which makes it easier to spot errors. I also tend to spend time analyzing the statistics of each data column, and many times I create scripts that automatically cleanse common errors from my dataset. I know how vital it is that the data be free of errors, and before I analyze any data I always cleanse it first.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Why do you want to be a fintech data analyst?", "answers": ["This is a broad question that many interviewers will ask because they want to understand why you're interested in this role and the fintech industry. Talk about what led you toward this career path, what kind of experience you're hoping to gain, what your professional passions are, and where you see yourself going as your career progresses.", "\"By nature, I'm analytical and detail-oriented, and from early on I was drawn to numbers and stats and data. I'm very interested in technology as well; when I was younger I would take apart and build computers, and I am the sort of person who likes to crunch numbers in Excel for fun. Some people find that kind of work tedious or monotonous, but I don't because I like to look for trends in the data. And I've been interested in finance and investing since college when I took my first investing course. So this role appeals to me because it combines several of my passions - data analysis, technology, and finance. I know that my personality is suited to it and that I will excel in this position.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Why do you want to work for our company?", "answers": ["Prior to the interview, it's a good idea to research the company so you can easily answer a question like this. You'll want to have an understanding of what the company does/sells and the type of customer it targets. Data analysts are hired by all kinds of companies in various industries; you'll want to specify why you are interested in working for a fintech company in particular.", "\"During college, I completed several summer internships that exposed me to the differences between working for a large corporate entity and a more nimble startup. Through these experiences, I discovered that I gravitate toward startups because I like being able to see the direct impact my work has within a company. Given that I've always had a strong interest in both finance and computers as well, I know that I'll be very happy working for and contributing to a fintech startup like yours.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What program do you prefer to use to analyze data?", "answers": ["There are numerous programs out there that can be used to perform data analysis. The interviewer wants to know that you're familiar with some of the commonly used programs. Explain which one is your favorite to use and why.", "\"Over the course of my career, I've had the opportunity to use many different data analysis programs, including Tableau, Google Fusion Tables, Google Search Operators, RapidMiner, Solver, and io. I'd say that my favorite one is Tableau because it has some great data visualization capabilities and it's also so easy to use. But I'm a quick learner and have used many different programs to date, so I'm confident that I can quickly adapt to whatever program(s) your company's data analysts use.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What would you do if you saw that data was missing or suspect?", "answers": ["There are times when fintech data analysts encounter incomplete datasets. The interviewer wants to know how you would handle this type of situation. If you have encountered this in the past, provide an example and explain how you handled it. It's important to emphasize that you know how important it is that the data you're working with be complete and accurate so your final conclusions are correct.", "\"There have been many times in the past when I've worked on projects and the datasets have contained missing or wrong information. In fact, it happens all the time! There are various methods that can be used to help resolve this issue, including kNN imputation, which I've used before to calculate and fill in missing data. Ultimately, the goal is to work with accurate data so during every project I make sure that any suspect data has been removed during the data profiling and cleansing stages and that any missing data has been replaced before I move forward with the data analysis process.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Walk me through the steps you typically take during a data analysis project.", "answers": ["There are several standardized steps that are generally taken by fintech data analysts during a project. The interviewer wants you to list and explain them so they understand how you typically tackle and complete a project. You will want to show that you are organized and that you consider the project's business goals before you get started.", "\"With any project, I always start by determining what the objectives are and what my manager needs from me. This helps me to decide what data sources will provide the information I need. I look for reliable and verified sources, and then I work on obtaining the data. Once I have it, I check it out, clean it, put it into an organized format, and then validate it. At this point, it's time to mine the data or, in other words, look for patterns and correlations within it. Finally, I create a report and/or present my findings to my manager.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What did you like and dislike about the culture of your last company?", "answers": ["Prior to the interview, you'll want to research the company you're interviewing for so you know what it does, who its target customer is, what industry it's in, and what its culture is like. Sometimes it's possible to learn about a company's culture by visiting their social media pages. When you answer this question, you'll want to cite the reasons why you think you'll fit into this company. Some reasons can include its size, how formal or informal their dress code, and whether or not the employees get together socially outside of work.", "\"The last company I worked for was great in many regards, but during my time there I realized that I would be much happier working for a company that is a bit more relaxed. The dress code was very formal there, and one thing that appeals to me about your company's culture is its more casual dress code. I'm also drawn to the smaller size of your company. Working for a larger company had its perks, but ultimately I am attracted to the flatter hierarchy of your company and the ability to see the direct impact of my work. Finally, while the employees at my last job were great people and extremely smart, I am drawn to the tenets your company appears to espouse:  namely, work hard/play hard and getting together socially outside of work to give back to the community.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is your biggest accomplishment to date?", "answers": ["An interviewer can find out a lot about someone by how they answer this question. Prior to the interview, think about some successes you've had in your life and how you might talk about them. You'll want to choose an accomplishment to discuss that can somehow be related to the fintech data analyst role and that shows positive qualities about you.", "\"Winning a Kaggle competition. So as you can see on my resume, I majored in business so my schooling wasn't really focused on computers or data per se. When I came out of college, I worked in business development, and although I enjoyed certain aspects of it, I felt drawn to data. In my off-hours, I would track different sports and wellness stats in Excel for fun. Eventually, I discovered a website called Kaggle and started competing in their online data analyst competitions. Not long ago, I won my first competition, and I knew I needed to change the direction of my career. I have continued to build my data skills through online courses and competitions.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "How would your boss and co-workers describe you?", "answers": ["This question allows the interviewer to learn more about who you are in order to determine if you will be a good fit for the fintech data analyst role. Be honest, but make sure to talk about qualities that would be favorable in this position. For instance, you might mention that you are a hard worker, analytical, detail-oriented, patient, a good communicator, collaborative, passionate about finance and investing, and/or not easily bored. This is a chance to really sell yourself.", "\"I think my current boss and co-workers would have plenty of positive things to say about me. First, I take ownership of my responsibilities and meet deadlines. If a task is added to my plate, I manage my time and resources to make sure I get it done to the best of my ability quickly and efficiently. I believe they would also say that I am a hard worker and someone who can proactively handle stress. If I start to get tired of working on a dataset, I'll take a short break so I can come back recharged and ready to tackle it. I also think they would call me analytical; I'm the person who gets called on to keep track of the stats for the company fantasy sports competitions because I can make quick calculations and they can trust me to record everything. Finally, I believe they'd mention my interest in investing since I usually spend my lunchbreak discussing my latest stocks picks.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What motivates you?", "answers": ["If the interviewer were to ask this question to someone in sales, their answer might be money in the form of commissions. A fintech data analyst, on the other hand, would likely be driven by other motivations. Not that earning a good salary isn't important to you, but the interviewer will want to hear that you're also driven by the desire to discover previously unknown trends in the data, to solve business problems, and to finish all the tasks on your to-do list.", "\"I would say that I'm mainly motivated by a job well done. I have a very strong work ethic that was instilled in me by my parents, and when my manager gives me a task I strive to complete it efficiently and in a timely manner so I can earn their approval and know that I did it to the best of my ability. Second, I tend to view data as a puzzle, and I am driven by the challenge of solving the 'puzzle.' So I don't just get my work done for my manager; I get it done so I can rest easy in knowing that I tackled the data and extracted all the insights I could from it.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What are your goals for the future?", "answers": ["Most interviewers are looking for a candidate to hire who will want to stay with the company for some time after they've been trained. This question is their way of scoping out what your future plans are and whether they include staying with the company or moving on. Be honest in your answer but definitely emphasize your loyalty and desire to grow within the company.", "\"As someone who has been in the fintech data analysis field for several years now, I know that this is the career for me and what I want to continue doing. Professionally, my goals include continuing to gain more knowledge and experience so that I can eventually move into a management role. I really look up to my current manager and would love to lead a team of fintech data analysts one day as well. I am coming into this experience with the hope that I will be able to stay with the company for the long term, as long as I'm continuing to grow and learn.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Can you tell me about a difficult work situation and how you overcame it?", "answers": ["The interviewer wants to know how you act when you're put into a challenging or stressful situation. You will want to give an example of when this happened to you. Explain the situation, what your role was, what actions you took, and what you learned from the experience. Be sure to emphasize the lessons you learned and carried with you.", "\"At my last job, I was teamed up with a colleague for a project that had a tight deadline. When my coworker and I initially met to discuss the objectives of the project, we decided to divvy up the workload so that we could get everything done in time to meet our deadline. When we came together after working apart on our separate project portions, I was surprised to discover that my colleague had not validated his data before moving on to other stages in the process. In my opinion, this made his final conclusions unreliable because I wasn't sure that they were based on accurate data. I ended up escalating the issue by meeting privately with my manager and expressing my concerns. We then met together with my colleague who agreed that our concerns were valid. In order to meet our deadline and present correct conclusions, I stayed late with my colleague and helped him re-do his portion of the work. In the end, I learned that when I'm working with someone new I need to communicate my expectations upfront about how important validating and cleansing the data is and then occasionally check in on them throughout the project to ensure that it's been done.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "How do you combat boredom during a long project?", "answers": ["At times, fintech data analysts work on projects that others might find tedious and boring. The interviewer wants to find someone to fill this role who in general doesn't find working with large datasets to be monotonous. At times, though, no matter how much you might like working with data, you may get temporarily frustrated or tired of it. Discuss the ways you combat these feelings so you can come back to a project recharged and in the right frame of mind.", "\"Generally speaking, I am the type of person who is very happy to work independently at my desk for hours at a time. I find numbers and metrics and stats to be fascinating, and I really enjoy when I'm given a large dataset to work on. The reality of this type of job, however, is that I spend hours at a time looking at data on a computer screen. Like anyone, sometimes I need a break. If this happens, I'll take a quick walk outside or a five-minute break in the kitchen while I eat a healthy snack. I also take advantage of my lunchbreak to chat with others and take my mind off the problem I'm solving. These occasional, quick breaks throughout the day give my eyes and brain a rest and allow me to come back to the data with a fresh new outlook.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What kind of challenges do fintech data analysts face?", "answers": ["While data analysts in general face many different types of difficulties in their everyday work, the interviewer wants to see if you can speak directly to challenges that exist for data analysts in the fintech field specifically. If possible, talk about challenges that you've faced personally within the industry and how you've overcome them. If you're coming from a different field, discuss challenges that you anticipate encountering in the financial industry.", "\"As someone who has worked as a fintech data analyst for a few years now, I would say that one of the biggest challenges I've personally faced at work is the need to manually update ever-changing information. Much of our data comes from the stock market, which obviously changes on a daily basis, and at the last company I worked for we had to update a lot of this information by hand. I've become more knowledgeable about implementing automated processes, and this is something that I would look to do here at this company as well if it is needed. Automating the collection of this sort of real-time data makes it much easier for us to focus on data mining instead.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Errors can cost the company clients. How do you ensure your work is mistake-free?", "answers": ["Fintech data analysts need to be fully cognizant of how important it is that their work be error-free. When it comes to the data you're analyzing, it needs to be validated and cleansed so the insights you pull from it are accurate. When you collect data manually, it needs to be entered into the system correctly to prevent problems down the line. Tell the interviewer how you ensure that the work you do is as mistake-free as possible.", "\"By nature, I'm extremely detail-oriented so right off the bat I doublecheck nearly everything I do. Obviously, I know that I have to keep moving and can't spend a ton of time doing this, but it's something that I do automatically. If I enter data into the company's internal system manually, I skim my entries over before I submit them. And when it comes to validating and cleansing the data I'm working with, I never, ever take that lightly. I always put the full effort in because I know that without good data I can't end up with good results. Everything hinges on the data being clean and high-quality; I understand this and always take the time to make sure the data has been thoroughly validated and cleansed before I move on to the next stage in the process.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Tell me about a time when you had to learn a new method or tool.", "answers": ["There are always going to be new data analysis programs, tools, and internal processes being introduced. Such is the life of a fintech data analyst. The interviewer wants to know that you are adaptable and able to learn new methods as needed. Give an example of a time when you had to learn something new on the job. Explain how you did so successfully.", "\"When I was in college, I learned how to use Tableau to analyze and mine data, but the first job I got after college didn't use that program. Instead, they used a program called RapidMiner. I had to learn fast and on the job, but I'm happy to report that I picked it up quickly. When questions arose, particularly in the beginning as I was getting used to the new program, I either asked my manager or a coworker for help. I made sure to be polite with my requests and to schedule a good time for them to train. In very little time, I had a clear understanding of the program. I feel confident that I can quickly learn any new program, method, or tool.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "Our primary goal at this company is to make our clients happy. Within this role, how do you plan to provide excellent client service?", "answers": ["Most of the time, fintech data analysts don't directly interact with clients; however, there's an overriding element of customer service in all roles at a company. The interviewer wants to know what customer service means to you within this role. Discuss what strategies you employ to keep the client top of mind while you do your work and complete projects.", "\"For me, when I spend time validating and cleansing the data I'm working on, my driving motivation is the end customer. I know that if I do a shoddy job in this part of the data analysis process, ultimately the final insights and conclusions that are pulled from the data won't be accurate, which will lead to a lower-quality product on our part. And in fintech, if our product isn't top-notch, this might very well result in a client losing money on an investment and leaving us. So I feel that by doing my best to ensure high-quality, accurate data, I help our company produce the best product possible for the customer.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "What is SQL and what kind of experience do you have using it?", "answers": ["One of the most important skills a fintech data analyst must master is the database language, SQL (Structured Query Language), as it can handle large datasets that Excel can't. Talk to the interviewer about your experience using SQL. If possible, cite an example or two of when you used it successfully during a project.", "\"I began to self-teach myself SQL years ago and later followed that up by taking an online SQL course that provided hands-on training. Since then, I've used it countless times during my career. Mastering Excel was important to be able to manipulate data, but SQL is on a whole other level. I have used it to manage and store data, build databases, change database structures, and relate multiple databases to each other. I honestly don't know how I'd do my job without the knowledge I have about SQL, and I look forward to applying that experience and know-how to this position.\""]}, {"topic": "Fintech+Data+Analyst", "question": "How do you make sure to use critical thinking when working on a project?", "answers": ["It's vital that a fintech data analyst be able to use data to find answers to questions but this means that the analyst needs to know what to ask in the first place. This means using critical thinking. To be able to succeed as an analyst, you need to be able to think like an analyst. Talk to the interviewer about your ability to think critically; provide examples and explain what steps you take to improve your critical thinking skills.", "\"When I start a project, one of the first steps I take is to think about what problem I'm trying to solve or question I'm trying to answer. This is key. Otherwise, my project won't have a solid direction and who knows where it will end up, which might just waste everyone's time. In order to make sure that I'm thinking critically during a project, I continually ask myself basic questions about it, which helps to keep me grounded and focused when searching for a solution. This also helps me to keep things simple instead of getting carried away with complicated explanations. I also remind myself to think outside-the-box and for myself, rather than to rely on what already exists.\""]}]